<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exact and certaine newes from the Siege at Yorke. And of many remarkable passages of our armys in those parts, extracted out of diverse letters which were sent by this last post from Hull, to a gentleman of Grayes-Inne. As also the taking of Mulgrave Castle, and in it Sir Walter Vavasour, Sir Peter Middletons eldest sonne, and other gentlemen of quality. Together with the relation of the Scots second army, advanced to Blithenooke in Northumberland, and their taking of Morpeth Castle. With many other remarkable observations.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E53_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860155</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860155</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155223</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84185)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155223)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 9:E53[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exact and certaine newes from the Siege at Yorke. And of many remarkable passages of our armys in those parts, extracted out of diverse letters which were sent by this last post from Hull, to a gentleman of Grayes-Inne. As also the taking of Mulgrave Castle, and in it Sir Walter Vavasour, Sir Peter Middletons eldest sonne, and other gentlemen of quality. Together with the relation of the Scots second army, advanced to Blithenooke in Northumberland, and their taking of Morpeth Castle. With many other remarkable observations.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Iuly 3. London, Printed for Mathew Walbanke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: 1. July 1644. Imprimatur Jo. Rushworth.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>York (England) --  History --  Siege, 1644 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155223:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Exact and certaine NEWES From the Siege at YORKE.</p>
            <p>And of many remarkable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of our Armys in thoſe parts, extracted out of diverſe Letters which were ſent by this laſt Poſt from <hi>Hull,</hi> to a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Grayes-Inne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo the taking of <hi>Mulgrave</hi> Caſtle, and in it Sir <hi>Walter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>avaſour,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Middletons</hi> eldeſt Sonne, and other Gentlemen of quality.</p>
            <p>Together with the Relation of the Scots ſecond Army, advanced to <hi>Blithenooke</hi> in <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and their taking of <hi>Morpeth</hi> Caſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With many other remarkable Obſervations<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> 3. London, Printed for <hi>Mathew Walbanke.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="excerpts_from_several_letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:155223:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155223:2"/>
            <head>AN EXTRACT OF Foure ſeverall Letters written from HULL, and ſent by this Poſt to a Gentleman of <hi>Grayes-Inne,</hi> by a prudentiall friend of his, newly returned thither from the Leaguer before YORKE.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p n="1">1<seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord of <hi>Manchesters</hi> Forces are daily in action, ſtraitning the beſieged in their quarters; and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering about <hi>Bowdan-Barre</hi> and the Mannor, and the beſieged frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iſſuing forth, and skirmiſhing. <hi>Iune</hi> 24, there were about 20 taken, and as many ſlaine on the Kings party, and two or three hurt and ſlaine on my Lord of <hi>Mancheſters,</hi> but this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported ſomething diverſly.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb facs="tcp:155223:3"/> 2. The Scots Forces for the moſt part ſtirre not, by reaſon the Enemie ſallied not out ſo oft againſt their quarters.</p>
               <p n="3">3. My Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is alſo often in action, about and againſt <hi>Monck-Barre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Prince <hi>Ruperts</hi> Army, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in horſe, is reported to be great, and a great part of brave horſe and good foo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, under the command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Leſley,</hi> are gone forth towards <hi>Rippon</hi> and thoſe parts, to meet and fight with them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. I beleeve (ſo far as I can conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) the Yorkiſts are neither quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor eaſily to be conquered, but are reſolved to try all extremity in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the comming and ayde of Prince <hi>Rupert;</hi> God turne all to the good of the Church and
<pb facs="tcp:155223:3"/>Common-wealth.</p>
               <p n="6">6. All the great and vaſt dales in the North-riding of <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their two ſtrong Caſtles of <hi>Midlan</hi> and <hi>Bolton,</hi> ſtand ſtill as formerly, to wit, in a neutrall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and to this day would never beare Armes, or pay Contributions, notwithſtanding all their ſeverall ſummons, threats, propoſitions ſent unto them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Colonell <hi>Charles Fairfax,</hi> a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent &amp; valiant Gentleman, hath again reduced moſt of the Biſhopricke of <hi>Durham</hi> to the obedience of the King and Parliament, and are now with about 1200. horſe about <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Sunderland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Laſt night newes came hither, (believed true and certaine) that a new Armie of Scots is come into <hi>Northumberland</hi> to <hi>Blythenooke,</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="tcp:155223:4"/>ten or twelve thouſand, and that they have already taken <hi>Morpeth</hi>-Caſtle, and that Colonell <hi>Clavering</hi> and the Scottiſh Lords with him, have reſted themſelves in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Theſe ſeas heere are full of danger and robberie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Out of another Letter.</head>
               <p n="10">10. Wee hold our ſiege yet, but are ſo prepared, that if Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> doe come, we are ready to meet him, we heare much of his advance this way, but no certainty which way he will fall into the Country.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Mulgrave</hi> Caſtle is taken, Sir <hi>Walter Vavaſor,</hi> Sir <hi>Peter Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> eldeſt ſonne, and divers others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:155223:4"/>
               <head>Out of another Letter.</head>
               <p n="12">12. There is about <hi>Whitby</hi> ſome Ordnance landed for us, of which Colonell <hi>Bointon</hi> having notice, did prepare Forces to conveigh them to <hi>Mulgrave</hi> Caſtle, (now in our hands) and had ſent Letters to ſome Troops in <hi>Holderneſſe</hi> to aſſiſt him: which Letters Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepting: and underſtanding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the deſigne, makes his ſtrength, &amp; goes and ſkirmiſheth with our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which a Maſter of a Ship on our ſide perceiving, ſent a ſhoare a Drake and 20 Muſquetiers which by a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take came to Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley,</hi> and ſo were ſurpriſed, but we heard this day that <hi>Whitby</hi> is taken by Colonell <hi>Bointon,</hi> and that Drake, with 40 men and Armes taken, and one
<pb facs="tcp:155223:5"/>
                  <hi>Newton</hi> is left Governour in it.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Wee now heare alſo from Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> who is about <hi>Rippon</hi> with his Army, that he cannot heare or learne that Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching any thing nearer <hi>Yorke,</hi> yet they are very cautious, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for him, leaſt that <hi>Vbiquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> ſteale on them unawares.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Our hopes are rather to ſtarve then ſtorme <hi>Yorke,</hi> but our deſire is to have it by compoſition and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Cawood</hi> Caſtle had like to have beene ſurpriſed, by a partie of Horſe from <hi>Pomfret,</hi> but was prevented by the vigilancie of the Guards, though ſome Priſoners eſcaped.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>1. July 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Jmprimatur,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>JO. RUSHWORTH.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
